Guide to the Woman's College Oral History Project records, 2003-2006. UA.25.05.0004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Woman's College Oral History Project records
2003-2006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Happer, Carolyn Murray, 1938-
UA.25.05.0004
0.5 Linear Feet
Nine interviews with alumnae of the Duke University Woman's College conducted by Carolyn Murray Happer from 2003 to 2004. Also includes one recording of alumnae reminisces from the 75th anniversary celebration of the Woman's College Library in 2006. Interviewees discuss their experiences and perceptions from their years at Duke University during the period of the co-ordinate college which existed from 1930 to 1972. Subjects interviewed include several class leaders, a member of the Duke family, and others who have had long established ties to the school after graduation. Also includes one recording of alumnae reminisces from the 75th anniversary celebration of the Woman's College Library in 2006.
26 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Cassette reference copies are available for consultation in the Reading Room. Interviews without release form are available for information use only. Copying or other uses will require permission from the interviewee.
Provenance
The Woman's College Oral History Project records were received by the University Archives as a gift in 2003-2004.
Biographical/Historical note
The Duke University Woman's College opened in the fall of 1930 as part of the expansion of Trinity College into Duke University. In 1924 James B. Duke established the Duke Endowment and gave funds to transform a small liberal arts college into a major university. From 1925 to 1927 the existing Trinity Campus (now Duke's East Campus) was rebuilt and transformed to become a residential campus for undergraduate women. From 1928 to 1930 Duke's new gothic West Campus and residential campus for undergraduate male students was constructed and known as Trinity College for Men. In 1972, the Men's and Women's colleges were merged to form Trinity College of Arts and Sciences.
In the Fall of 2002, the Woman's College marked the 30th anniversary of its merger with the Trinity College for Men with a reunion. Carolyn Murray Happer, Class of 1960, curated an exhibition on the history of Woman's College and decided to start an oral history interview project with alumnae for use in a proposed history of Woman's College.
Scope and Contents note
Carolyn Murray Happer interviewed nine alumnae who graduated from the period of 1931 to 1947. Her goal was to document the experiences and perceptions of women who attended Duke University during this period. In particular she wanted to know why they selected and how the Woman's College figured into that decision. She also explored her subject's position and negative experiences at Duke. Her interviewees include several class leaders, a member of the Duke family, and others who have had long established ties to the school after graduation.
Collection Arrangement
In addition to the interviews listed below, life history forms, and some interview summaries are available for some interviews and maintained in the collection control file. Reference cassette copies are available for all interviews.
Related Material
Alice M. Baldwin papers.
Duke University. University Archives.
Woman's College records.
Duke University. University Archives.
Oral history interviews; Happer, Carolyn Murray, 1938-; Lanning, Elizabeth Williams; Harris, Margaret A; Duke University. Woman's College -- Students; Crowell, Alice; Duke University. Woman's College -- History; Corbin, Charlotte; Greenberg, Bluma; Buschman, Barbara Perkins; Duke University. Woman's College; Semans, Mary Duke Biddle Trent; Merritt, Gertrude; Women in higher education -- North Carolina -- Durham; Women -- Education (Higher) -- North Carolina -- Durham
- Interviews, 2003-2004
  - Buschman, Barbara Perkins, 2003-09-29
    Scope and Contents
    Class of 1946. Buschman also worked at Duke from 1946 to 1993 in various positions. Her interview covers primarily her undergraduate years.
    - Reference audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA25050004-CS-0006)
  - Corbin, Charlotte, 2003-07-02
    Class of 1935. Former Duke Alumni Office employee.
    - Reference audiocassette 1 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA25050004-CS-0008)
    - Reference audiocassette 2 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA25050004-CS-0009)
  - Crowell, Alice, 2003-06-19
    Class of 1932.
    - Reference audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA25050004-CS-0007)
  - Greenberg, Bluma, 2003-09-23
    Class of 1947. Greenberg discussed how she was treated as a Jewish student at Duke during WWII as well as soldiers returning from the war to school.
    - Reference audiocassette 1 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA25050004-CS-0001)
    - Reference audiocassette 2 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA25050004-CS-0002)
    - Digital audio file, 0:44:20 (Digital-materials UA25050004-SET-0001, Audio-file UA25050004-CS-0001_01)
    - Digital audio file, 0:44:22 (Digital-materials UA25050004-SET-0001, Audio-file UA25050004-CS-0001_02)
    - Digital audio file, 0:19:00 (Digital-materials UA25050004-SET-0001, Audio-file UA25050004-CS-0002_01)
  - Harris, Margaret A., 2003-07-18
    Class of 1938 and Law School Class of 1940. Also served on the Board of Trustees, 1975-1987. Harris discusses her decision to attend Duke and her time in Law School
    - Reference audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA25050004-CS-0010)
  - Lanning, Elizabeth Williams, 2003-07-17
    Class of 1931. Married Duke professor John Tate Lanning. Lanning transferred to Duke from Queens and discusses social life, including her sorority and dances.
    - Reference audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA25050004-CS-0004)
    - Digital audio file (Digital-materials UA25050004-SET-0001, Audio-file UA25050004-CS-0004_001.wav)
  - Merritt, Gertrude, 2003-06-25
    Class of 1931. Long-time Duke librarian.
    - Reference audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA25050004-CS-0012)
  - Semans, Mary Duke Biddle Trent, 2004-02-06
    Class of 1939. Served on Board of Trustees, 1961-1981.
    - Reference audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA25050004-CS-0011)
  - Smith, Margaret Taylor, 2003-10-24
    Class of 1947.
    - Reference audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA25050004-CS-0005)
  - Woman's College Library reminiscences, 2006-03-23
    - Reference audiocassette (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA25050004-CS-0003)
    - Digital audio file, 0:43:57 (Digital-materials UA25050004-SET-0001, Audio-file UA25050004-CS-0003_01)
    - Digital audio file, 0:15:02 (Digital-materials UA25050004-SET-0001, Audio-file UA25050004-CS-0003_02)